<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<metadata>
    <idinfo>
        <citation>
            <citeinfo>
                <origin>USA National Phenology Network</origin>
                <pubdate>2016</pubdate>
                <title>Phenology Observation Data</title>
                <geoform>Tabular Digital Data</geoform>
                <onlink>http://dx.doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N1V</onlink>
            </citeinfo>
        </citation>
        <descript>
            <abstract>This suite of datasets consists of in-situ phenology data on over 1000 species of plants and animals (2009-present) and data on lilacs and honeysuckles (1956-present), across the United States. These data were collected by citizen and professional observers, and are archived and distributed by the USA National Phenology Network (www.usanpn.org). Protocols are available in Denny et al, 2014. Datum is WGS84.  This collection represents a suite of four data products: 1) Status and Intensity Data (phenophase status records of presence or absence of the phenophase, as well as information about the degree to which the phenophase was expressed for each individual plant or species of animal at a site, for each site visit), 2) Individual Phenometrics (estimates of the dates of all onsets and ends of a phenophase for individual plants and for animal species at a site during a user-defined time period), 3) Site Phenometrics (estimates of the dates of first onset and last end for a phenophase, averaged across individuals of the same species at a site, during a user-defined time period) and 4) Magnitude Phenometrics (a suite of eight metrics that describe the degree to which a phenophase is expressed across multiple individuals or sites, summarized for a given time interval). 
</abstract>
            <purpose>Datasets were developed by the USA National Phenology Network to better understand the response of plant and animal species to environmental variation and climate change, and to develop a baseline against which future phenological change may be measured.</purpose>
            <supplinf>Please find datafield metadata (entity and attribute information) at www.usanpn.org/files/metadata/all_datafield_descriptions.xlsx</supplinf>
        </descript>
        <timeperd>
            <timeinfo>
                <rngdates>
                    <begdate>19560101</begdate>
                    <enddate>PRESENT</enddate>
                </rngdates>
            </timeinfo>
            <current>Ground condition; data are made available in real-time.</current>
        </timeperd>
        <status>
            <progress>In work</progress>
            <update>Daily</update>
        </status>
        <spdom>
            <bounding>
                <westbc>-125.000</westbc>
                <eastbc>-67.000</eastbc>
                <northbc>72.000</northbc>
                <southbc>17.000</southbc>
            </bounding>
        </spdom>
        <keywords>
            <theme>
                <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
                <themekey>phenology</themekey>
                <themekey>ecology</themekey>
            </theme>
        </keywords>
        <accconst>Public</accconst>
        <useconst> USA National Phenology Network. Year of dataset access. Plant and Animal Phenology Data. Data type: [Status and Intensity, Individual Phenometrics, Site Phenometrics or Magnitude Phenometrics]. [Date range of data used] for Region: [Coordinates]. USA-NPN, Tucson, Arizona, USA. Data set accessed [Date] at http://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N1V
Example: USA National Phenology Network. 2017. Plant and Animal Phenology Data. Data type: Site Phenometrics. 01/01/2011-12/31/2016 for Region: 49.9375°, -66.4791667° (UR); 24.0625°, -125.0208333° (LL). USA-NPN, Tucson, Arizona, USA. Data set accessed 06/15/2017 at http://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N1</useconst>
        <ptcontac>
            <cntinfo>
                <cntorgp>
                    <cntorg>USA National Phenology Network</cntorg>
                    <cntper>Alyssa Rosemartin</cntper>
                </cntorgp>
                <cntpos>Coordinator</cntpos>
                <cntaddr>
                    <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
                    <address>1311 E 4th St</address>
                    <city>Tucson</city>
                    <state>AZ</state>
                    <postal>85721</postal>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </cntaddr>
                <cntvoice>+1-520-621-8571</cntvoice>
                <cntemail>alyssa@usanpn.org</cntemail>
            </cntinfo>
        </ptcontac>
        <datacred>Data were provided by the USA National Phenology Network, with funding and leadership from the United States Geological Survey, and contributions from many partners and Nature’s Notebook observers. </datacred>
    </idinfo>
    <dataqual>
        <attracc>
            <attraccr>Attribute accuracy tests are described in an information sheet: https://www.usanpn.org/files/shared/files/QA-QC_tech_info_sheet_v2.4.pdf</attraccr>
        </attracc>
        <logic>Logic tests are described in an information sheet: https://www.usanpn.org/files/shared/files/QA-QC_tech_info_sheet_v2.4.pdf</logic>
        <complete>Data provided as-is.</complete>
        <posacc>
            <horizpa>
                <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
            </horizpa>
            <vertacc>
                <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
            </vertacc>
        </posacc>
        <lineage>
            <procstep>
                <procdesc>Processing is described in a forthcoming Techniques and Methods report.</procdesc>
                <procdate>Ongoing</procdate>
            </procstep>
        </lineage>
    </dataqual>
    <spdoinfo>
        <direct>Point</direct>
        <ptvctinf>
            <sdtsterm>
                <sdtstype>Point</sdtstype>
            </sdtsterm>
        </ptvctinf>
    </spdoinfo>
    <eainfo>
        <overview>
            <eaover>Data dictionaries are temporarily available at www.usanpn.org/files/metadata/all_datafield_descriptions.xlsx and www.usanpn.org/files/metadata/ancillary_datafield_descriptions.xlsx and will be included in forthcoming  Techniques and Methods report.</eaover>
            <eadetcit>Citation pending.</eadetcit>
        </overview>
    </eainfo>
    <distinfo>
        <distrib>
            <cntinfo>
                <cntorgp>
                    <cntorg>USA National Phenology Network</cntorg>
                    <cntper>Theresa Crimmins</cntper>
                </cntorgp>
                <cntpos>Assistant Director</cntpos>
                <cntaddr>
                    <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
                    <address>1311 E 4th St</address>
                    <city>Tucson</city>
                    <state>AZ</state>
                    <postal>85721</postal>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </cntaddr>
                <cntvoice>+1-520-621-8523</cntvoice>
                <cntemail>theresa@usanpn.org</cntemail>
            </cntinfo>
        </distrib>
        <distliab>These data are preliminary or provisional and are subject to revision. They are being provided to meet the need for timely best science. The data have not received final approval by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and are provided on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from the authorized or unauthorized use of the data.</distliab>
        <stdorder>
            <digform>
                <digtinfo>
                    <formname>https://www.usanpn.org/results/data</formname>
                </digtinfo>
                <digtopt>
                    <onlinopt>
                        <computer>
                            <networka>
                                <networkr>http://doi.org/10.5066/F78S4N1V</networkr>
                            </networka>
                        </computer>
                    </onlinopt>
                </digtopt>
            </digform>
            <digform>
                <digtinfo>
                    <formname>Machine accessible JSON endpoint for Phenology Observation Data: Status and Intensity Data</formname>
                </digtinfo>
                <digtopt>
                    <onlinopt>
                        <computer>
                            <networka>
                                <networkr>http://www.usanpn.org/npn_portal/observations/getObservations.json</networkr>
                            </networka>
                        </computer>
                        <accinstr>Instructions provided at: https://docs.google.com/document/d/1yNjupricKOAXn6tY1sI7-EwkcfwdGUZ7lxYv7fcPjO8/edit</accinstr>
                    </onlinopt>
                </digtopt>
            </digform>
            <digform>
                <digtinfo>
                    <formname>Machine accessible JSON endpoint for Phenology Observation Data: Individual Phenometrics</formname>
                </digtinfo>
                <digtopt>
                    <onlinopt>
                        <computer>
                            <networka>
                                <networkr>http://www.usanpn.org/npn_portal/observations/getSummarizedData.json</networkr>
                            </networka>
                        </computer>
                        <accinstr>Instructions provided at: https://docs.google.com/document/d/1yNjupricKOAXn6tY1sI7-EwkcfwdGUZ7lxYv7fcPjO8/edit</accinstr>
                    </onlinopt>
                </digtopt>
            </digform>
            <digform>
                <digtinfo>
                    <formname>Machine accessible JSON endpoint for Phenology Observation Data: Site Phenometrics</formname>
                </digtinfo>
                <digtopt>
                    <onlinopt>
                        <computer>
                            <networka>
                                <networkr>http://www.usanpn.org/npn_portal/observations/getSiteSummarizedData.json</networkr>
                            </networka>
                        </computer>
                        <accinstr>Instructions provided at: https://docs.google.com/document/d/1yNjupricKOAXn6tY1sI7-EwkcfwdGUZ7lxYv7fcPjO8/edit</accinstr>
                    </onlinopt>
                </digtopt>
            </digform>
            <fees>None.</fees>
        </stdorder>
    </distinfo>
    <metainfo>
        <metd>20160801</metd>
        <metc>
            <cntinfo>
                <cntperp>
                    <cntper>Alyssa Rosemartin</cntper>
                    <cntorg>USA National Phenology Network</cntorg>
                </cntperp>
                <cntpos>Coordinator</cntpos>
                <cntaddr>
                    <addrtype>Mailing and Physical</addrtype>
                    <address>1311 E 4th St</address>
                    <city>Tucson</city>
                    <state>AZ</state>
                    <postal>85721</postal>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </cntaddr>
                <cntvoice>+1-520-621-8571</cntvoice>
                <cntemail>alyssa@usanpn.org</cntemail>
            </cntinfo>
        </metc>
        <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
        <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    </metainfo>
</metadata>